Okay,
בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף למד, daf lamed,
thirty, and we begin in earnest the third פרק. perek. We began
it just briefly yesterday. Where I'll actually, for the sake, because it's
a short דף daf and for the sake of full context, start
us again from although we had finished the דף daf yesterday, but
start us from the גמרא Gemara towards the bottom of כ"ט עמוד
ב', chaf tet amud bet, right after the משנה. Mishnah. And this
is going to hone in on the first two statements of the
משנה: Mishnah: לולב הגזול והיבש פסול. Lulav hagazul vehayavesh pasul.
The first statement with the two invalidities. A stolen and a dried
לולב lulav is invalid. And I've already pointed out a very important
principle that the גמרא Gemara will sort of state in almost in
passing, which is that a lot of the invalidities of the לולב
lulav and the אתרוג etrog or the other מינים minim on that
have to do with their aesthetics and appearance,
is attributed to the use of the word הדר hadar in the
verse, פרי עץ הדר, peri etz hadar, the fruit of a beautiful
tree. But that הדר hadar is used to understand that that has
to be a character of all of the מינים minim of the
לולב, lulav, all of the components of the לולב. lulav. רש"י Rashi
on the משנה Mishnah interprets it in a larger context of זה
קלי ואנוהו, Zeh Keli V'Anvehu, beautifying מצוות. mitzvot. Even though normally that
is not something that is an absolute requirement and doesn't invalidate a
מצוה, mitzvah, here he understands presumably that the word הדר hadar is
coming to say that here that aspect of having a beautiful מצוה
mitzvah is central and without it is invalid. But anyway, it is
rooted in the use of the word of the verse of הדר.
hadar. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. כפסיק
ותני, Ka pasik v'tani, says the גמרא. Gemara. The משנה, Mishnah, a
פסקא ותני paska vetani means like just, you know, sort of states,
you know, categorically
without distinction, and states and states that a stolen or a dried
up לולב lulav is invalid, makes no distinction. לא שנא ביום טוב
ראשון ולא שנא ביום טוב שני. Lo shna b'yom tov rishon v'lo
shna b'yom tov sheni. Regardless of whether you're talking about the first
day יום טוב Yom Tov or the second day. Now, the second
day יום טוב, Yom Tov, it's clear from context from what all
the ראשונים Rishonim say, does not mean our second day יום טוב
Yom Tov of גלות. Galus. It means חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Okay,
so whether it's the biblical מצוה mitzvah on the first day or
the rabbinic מצוה mitzvah on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, because the verse
says, ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון, u'lekachtem lachem bayom harishon, take on the
first day. And then the end of the verse is, פרי עץ
הדר כפות תמרים וענף עץ עבות וערבי נחל, peri etz hadar kpot
tmarim v'anaf etz avot v'arvei nachal, and the end of the verse
is, ושמחתם לפני ה' אלקיכם שבעת ימים, u'smachtem lifnei Hashem Elokeichem shivat
yamim, rejoice before God seven days. So the rabbis understand that seven
days there is before God. If you're in the Temple, the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you take the לולב lulav all seven days. But
outside of the Temple, or some say outside is ירושלים Yerushalayim outside
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but like outside of the Temple, you only take the
לולב lulav ביום הראשון. bayom harishon. The only reason we take the
לולב lulav and the אתרוג etrog the other days, the days of
חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, is because of a זכר למקדש, zecher l'mikdash,
to commemorate the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So those are rabbinic. So
the גמרא Gemara is saying the fact that the משנה Mishnah just
says invalid without distinction sounds like לא שנא ביום טוב ראשון ולא
שנא ביום טוב שני, lo shna b'yom tov rishon lo shna b'yom
tov sheni, regardless on the first day or the first day or
the later days, it's always invalid, whether the biblical מצוה mitzvah or
the rabbinic מצוה. mitzvah. בשלמא יבש, Bishlama yavesh, I understand if it's
dried up why it's invalid throughout. הדר בעינן וליכא, Hadar ba'inan ve'leka,
and there's that key word. You need הדר. hadar. You need it
to be beautiful. And if it doesn't have a if it falls
below a minimum aesthetic quality, it's invalid. And that logically applies for
the whole week.
אלא גזול, Ela gazul, but stolen, בשלמא יום ראשון דכתיב לכם משלכם,
bishlama yom rishon d'chtiv lachem mishelachem, I get it the first day,
it has to you can't have it stolen, it has to be
yours. Because it says yours, לכם, lachem, ולקחתם לכם. u'lekachtem lachem. אלא
ביום טוב שני אמאי לא? Ela b'yom tov sheni, amai lo? Why
not the second days? Why should it have to belong to you?
Now, before we get to the answer, again, it's very just an
important point to stop here and say is, why does the גמרא
Gemara assume that you don't also need לכם lachem all seven days?
Why does it take it for granted that הדר hadar applies all
seven days on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, maybe לכם lachem should as
well? Now, one answer could just be that it's not based on
anything in the verse, it's just based on the fact that we,
you know, sort of like on an accepted הלכה. halacha. And we
know as an accepted הלכה halacha that you can use a borrowed
לולב lulav and אתרוג etrog on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So it's
just saying like, you know, I'm not saying what you know, why
logically לכם lachem should be different than הדר, hadar, but we just
happen to know that you can use borrowed לולב lulav and אתרוג
etrog on the other days. So why should stolen be a problem?
That's maybe like the easiest way. Just start from a point of
fact that we know you can use borrowed on the other days.
But the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that, and ראשונים Rishonim sort of
this pushes ראשונים Rishonim to ask what determines which invalidities are only
on the first day and which ones are on the rest of
the days. And why should there be a difference between the aesthetic
aspect and the ownership aspect? So the תוספות Tosafos and רש"י Rashi
basically say that look, the rest of the days are rabbinic. So
we're not going to demand everything at the rabbinic level than we
demand at the biblical, even though often we pattern rabbinic after biblical.
But things that are really
sort of central or they touch on deeper themes and here's where
רש"י Rashi brings up his idea that הדר זה קלי ואנוהו Hadar
Zeh Keili Ve'anveihu is beautifying the מצוה. Mitzvah. So it touches on
a deeper theme. That's a type of a thing that rabbinically we're
going to insist on even on the other days. That's an important
idea, having a beautiful מצוה. Mitzvah. Something that's more like a technical
issue, like owning it, whether you own it or it's borrowed, that's
not so central and we're not going to demand that on the
other days. So there's more of a logic to demand it be
beautiful or to demand aesthetic than to demand a question
of ownership. Another way of saying that is also that הדר Hadar
and the beauty and the quality sort of describe something about the
very nature of the object that you're taking. It's like a different
מצוה Mitzvah if you're taking a different type of an אתרוג, Esrog,
an אתרוג Esrog that could be all shriveled up, right? It's different
physically what you're doing. Whether you own it or not is something
that is not visible and is not somehow part of the physical
reality of what you are doing. So again, another way of explaining
that the issue of ownership is more tangential and therefore it's assumed
to be not going to be required on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed.
So that's the basic approach that רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos say.
There's a lot of other discussion about it. First of all, some
try to link it to the very phrasing of the verse. ולקחתם
לכם
ביום הראשון פרי עץ הדר. U'lekachtem lachem bayom harishon pri eitz hadar.
The word לכם Lachem precedes יום הראשון. Yom harishon. So לכם Lachem
is only limited to the first day. הדר Hadar comes after the
word יום ראשון Yom rishon and this is for all days, which
is very nice except we're talking here about the rabbinic מצוה, Mitzvah,
so how it would be linked on the phrasing of the verse
is not so clear. The last thing I'll say about it at
this point is that there's a major, major debate of the ראשונים
Rishonim about whether the invalidities apply on חול המועד Chol HaMoed because
there was a reality that in Europe or whatever in the time
of the ראשונים, Rishonim, it was very hard to get a כשר
לולב Kosher Lulav and אתרוג. Esrog. And maybe you could have one
כשר לולב Kosher Lulav and אתרוג Esrog in the whole town. So
how do you deal with it? So some ראשונים Rishonim basically say
you're right, all of these problems remain problems on חול המועד Chol
HaMoed and maybe you're not יוצא Yotzei or maybe they came up
with an idea of saying like maybe it's like you're doing it
sort of as a זכר. Zecher. You'll take it and you'll make
a ברכה Bracha to remember the מצוה Mitzvah but technically you're not
יוצא. Yotzei. That's a lot of what was said in אשכנז. Ashkenaz.
In ספרד Sefarad what was said is actually even when things are
not satisfy הדר, Hadar, even when things are not aesthetic and they
are dried up and shriveled because they would have cases where they
would keep a לולב Lulav and אתרוג Esrog from previous years. And
the only לולב Lulav and אתרוג Esrog they would use is the
one they've been using for the last ten years, so it was
going to be יבש. Yavesh. So a number of ראשונים Rishonim said,
okay, you're not יוצא, Yotzei, but you can still take it and
make a ברכה Bracha as a זכר. Zecher. That's what they said
in אשכנז. Ashkenaz. In ספרד Sefarad a lot what they said was,
no, actually you are יוצא Yotzei with it at least on חול
המועד. Chol HaMoed. And that you're יוצא Yotzei with the invalid stuff
on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So what do you do with our
גמרא? Gemara? Our גמרא Gemara says יבש Yavesh is a problem on
the other days. So the רמב"ן Ramban has a brilliant
answer. I don't know if it's פשט, Pshat, but he has a
brilliant answer. He says that actually when we talk about the other
days of יום טוב Yom Tov and we talk about חול המועד,
Chol HaMoed, we're not talking about the rabbinic מצוה. Mitzvah. We're talking
about the biblical מצוה Mitzvah in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And
that's where we can say, okay, in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
you don't need לכם Lachem on the other days but you need
it to be הדר. Hadar. And maybe exactly because the verse has
the word לכם Lachem coming before ביום הראשון Bayom harishon and הדר
Hadar becomes the word after יום ראשון. Yom rishon. That's in terms
of the biblical מצוה. Mitzvah. We're talking about doing it in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. That would be so fun to just assume
פשט Pshat that's the context. But when we're talking only about the
rabbinic מצוה Mitzvah nowadays, then even if it's dried up you're still
יוצא. Yotzei. So
quite fascinating. So again two important things to understand from this line
of the גמרא Gemara before we proceed. Number one is that
why is הדר Hadar required on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, the aesthetic
aspects and not ownership? Probably the simplest explanation is that הדר Hadar
is a much more deeper idea of a beautiful מצוה. Mitzvah. There's
also much more central about the character of the act, whereas the
issue of ownership is a much more secondary type of an external
requirement, a non-physical requirement, and therefore it's something that we're assuming does
not apply on the other days and we know you can use
a borrowed לולב Lulav and אתרוג Esrog on the other days. And
that's the line of distinction between issues about the aesthetics, which remain
an issue, and ownership. But also remember that the ראשוני ספרד Rishonei
Sfarad basically said against the simple sense of this גמרא, Gemara, they
actually said that you can have a dried up לולב Lulav on
the other days and that actually was a reality. And the רמב"ן
Ramban deals with it by saying that either we rule against this
גמרא Gemara or we
say... Okay, but we'll deal with the simple understanding that in חול
המועד Chol HaMoed it has to have the aesthetic requirement, but it
doesn't have to have the ownership issues. And now we get back
to the גמרא'ס Gemara's question, which is, so who cares if it's
stolen or not? Quick question.
Yeah? I'm surprised that this situation would come up in Sephardi lands
because palm trees and citrus fruit grow very easily in the Mediterranean
in the Middle East.
Well, but some Sephardi lands were Spain, so... Spain is on the
Mediterranean.
Good question, I don't know.
I would like to suggest methodologically that we define by definition all
of the statements of חכמי ספרד Chachmei Sfarad as the פשט. P'shat.
Okay,
you've now used up your one question for tonight. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, so back to the question. So back
to back to so back to the question. Okay, so you don't
have to own it, but we understand that it has to be
aesthetic, it has to be הדר. Hadar. So we understand the basis
of the problem, but why is stolen a problem on the other
days when you could use borrowed? So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר
לו, Amar Lo, אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחי, Amar
Rabi Yochanan mishum Rabi Shimon ben Yochai, it says רבי יוחנן Rabi
Yochanan in the name of רבי שמעון בן יוחי, Rabi Shimon ben
Yochai, משום דהוה mishum d'hava top line of עמוד א', Amud Alef,
מצווה הבאה בעבירה, Mitzvah HaBa'ah B'Aveirah,
because it's a מצווה Mitzvah coming through the agency of sin. You're
only able to have this לולב Lulav because you stole it, and
that is invalid. Now, where do you know that the idea of
a מצווה Mitzvah coming through sin is invalid? שנאמר: She'ne'emar: והבאתם גזול
את הפיסח ואת החולה. V'heveisem gazul es hapisayach v'es hacholeh.
And you shall, if you and if you bring the stolen and
the lame, not פסח, Pesach, פיסח, Pisayach, the lame and the sick
animal. The end of the פסוק Pasuk says, וירצה לפני השם V'hayertzeh
lifnei Hashem I think is the end of the פסוק. Pasuk. Will
this be desired by God if you bring this type of an
animal as a sacrifice? So it includes the issue of lame and
the problem of lame and the problem of stolen. גזול דומיא דפיסח,
Gazul dumya d'pisayach,
stolen is made similar, compared to a lame. מה פיסח לית ליה
תקנתא, Ma pisayach leis lei takanta, the same way a lame animal
has no is invalid and has no way that it can ever
be fixed, right, is never going to remain invalid, אף גזול לית
ליה תקנתא, Af gazul leis lei takanta, so even a stolen animal
or object here we would say by a לולב, Lulav, but for
now we'll say an animal, cannot be fixed. לא שנא לפני ייאוש
לא שנא לאחר ייאוש. Lo shena lifnei ye'ush, lo shena achar ye'ush.
It doesn't matter whether it is before the owner has given up
hope, ייאוש Ye'ush is when the owner gives up hope, or even
after the owner has given up hope, it remains invalid. Okay, בשלמא
לפני ייאוש, Bishlama lifnei ye'ush,
I understand why you can't use a stolen animal for a קרבן
Korban before the owner has given up hope. אדם כי יקריב מכם
אמר רחמנא. Adam ki yakriv mikem amra rachmana. Look at that, quoting
a פסוק Pasuk right from the beginning of this week's פרשה. Parsha.
If a person brings from amongst you a קרבן, Korban, so it
has to be מכם, Mikem, the קרבן Korban has to come from
you, from the person who's bringing it. ולאו דידיה הוא. V'lav didei
hu. So you're not it's not your animal. So if you try
to sanctify your animal and the and that you had stolen, you're
giving a קרבן Korban from something that isn't yours. אלא לאחר ייאוש,
Ela achar ye'ush,
but after the owner's, if ראובן Reuven stole it from שמעון Shimon
and שמעון Shimon then says, 'oi, I'm never going to get that
sheep back,' and then ראובן Reuven brought it as a, sanctified it
and brought it as a קרבן. Korban. הקנייה בייאוש. Hakanya b'ye'ush. So
so ראובן Reuven should now own it because the principle is that
after the original owner gives up hope, somebody takes it, it becomes
theirs. Like if I lose a lost object on the street and
my wallet and you pick it up before I've given up hope
of return, you have to return it to me. But if I
say, 'oh my god I lost my wallet I'm never going to
get it back, there are no honest people in this world,' and
then you find it, then it becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy, then you
get to keep it because you picked it up after ייאוש, Ye'ush,
after I gave up hope.
So the גמרא Gemara here is assuming the same is true if
somebody stole a sheep and the original owner was מיאש, Miya'esh, gave
up hope, that now this sheep becomes belongs to the גנב Gannav
or the גזלן, Gazlan, and now it's his. So why can't he
give it as a קרבן? Korban? Now I should say, I mean
some of these huge תוספות Tosafos in here which make it a
very short דף Daf today, get to this question of do we
really say that ייאוש Ye'ush allows the גזלן Gazlan to take possession
of it? In the case of the אבידה, Aveidah, if I find
the lost wallet
after the owner after the owner's given up hope, fine, I can
take it because when I first encounter it, it's sort of like
the owner has already detached himself from it, given up hope. But
let's say I find the wallet and then the owner gives up
hope once the wallet's in my hand. What do you think the
הלכה Halacha is? Can I keep it then? I pick up the
wallet, the owner hasn't given up hope,
and then
I have an obligation to return it. And then even if after
he gives up hope, right, once I encountered it and I picked
it up with an obligation to return it, his giving up hope
doesn't change things. So the same is generally true about a גזלן.
Gazlan. I steal something, and then the owner gives up hope, I
still don't own it, I still have to return it, I still
I was the one who stole. Maybe somebody takes it from me,
they're like you know from from their perspective they're encountering it after
ייאוש. Ye'ush. So if they, if I sell it to someone now
they might own it because they're now getting it בהפקר, B'hefker, but
when I took it, I have an obligation to return it immediately.
His giving up hope doesn't change things doesn't let me own it.
So why does the גמרא Gemara assume that after יאוש Yeush the
גזלן Gezlen now owns it? So there are two explanations. One is
that there actually is another opinion out there in the גמרא. Gemara.
There actually is an opinion that יאוש כדי, Yeush kidei, יאוש Yeush
all by itself קני Kani
transfers ownership. And it doesn't mean that I have to first there
has to be יאוש Yeush and then I have to take possession
of it. Even if I already stole it and then the owner
gives up hope, once he's given up hope now and then once
maybe it's different than if you picked it up to return it.
If you picked it up to return it, you've brought it back
into the owner's sphere. He might not be aware of it, but
your picking it up to return it puts it back in his
sphere. But if I took it to steal it and I'm pulling
it away from him, then as soon as he gives up hope
even after I took possession of it, I'm going to own it.
And that's the simple sense of this גמרא. Gemara. That this גמרא
Gemara assumes that יאוש Yeush by itself works for a גנב Ganav
and a גזלן. Gezlen. There's another possibility I'll just mention because it'll
also come up on the עמוד ב Amud Bet in a different
way
is that יאוש Yeush doesn't do it by itself. But if I
stole his sheep and then I sanctified it after יאוש, Yeush, so
the act of sanctifying it it's like handing it over to הקדש.
Hekdesh. If I handed it over to Charlie, he would get it
and he would own it. So my act of sanctifying it changes
it and makes it something that allows me to own it. It's
not just the יאוש Yeush by itself, it's the change of identity
and ownership that comes with the sanctification. But that's getting a little
complicated. We're going to assume the simple sense of the גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara says I stole it. The גמרא Gemara assumes that
once the owners give up hope and I'm stealing it, now I
fully own it. So if I fully own this sheep after I've
stolen it, why can't I bring it as a קרבן? Korban? So
let's take a look. So why not? לא שנא לפני? Lo shna
lifnei? So בשלמא לפני יאוש Bishlama lifnei Yeush before the owner gave
up hope, אדם כי יקריב מכם אמר רחמנא Adam ki yakriv mikem
amar rachmana it has to be yours, so לאו דידיה Lav didei
it's not his. אלא אחר יאוש Ela achar Yeush but after the
owner has given up hope קניה ביאוש, Kanyeh beyeush, yeah now I
own it, so why can't I bring it as a קרבן? Korban?
אלא לאו משום דהוי ליה מצוה הבאה בעבירה. Ela lav mishum de-havei
leih mitzvah haba'ah be'aveirah. It's a מצוה Mitzvah that comes through sin.
Since it's stolen, that completely stigmatizes it, invalidates it, just like if
it were lame and you can't use it. And same by the
לולב. Lulav. You forget that there's no requirement, you can use a
borrowed לולב Lulav on the other days, but stolen invalidates. Now I'm
going to discuss what the exactly how to frame the parameters of
מצוה הבאה בעבירה Mitzvah haba'ah be'aveirah in a minute. Let me just
read what the next path says. Okay, ואמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי
שמעון בר יוחאי, Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan also says in the name of רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, מאי דכתיב Mai d'chtiv what's meant by
the verse, כי אני ה' אוהב משפט, Ki ani Hashem ohev mishpat,
I God love justice, שונא גזל בעולה, Sonei gezel be'olah, I hate
גזל Gezel stolen objects in an עולה Olah in a burnt offering.
Again, it's particularly rooted in the world of קרבן. Korban. So what
does that mean? What's the point that God hates it? משל למלך
בשר ודם. Mashal lemelech basar vadam. It's a parable to a human
king, a king of flesh and blood, so I should say flesh
and bone, שהיה עובר על בית המכס She-hayah over al beit hamekhes
who was passing by the tax house. You know, where you have
to pay basically the
what is it like when you're importing things? You know, the גמרא
Gemara often talks about מוכסין Mokhsin custom, the custom house. אמר לעבדיו,
Amar le'avadav, תנו מכס למוכס. Tnu mekhes lamokhes. So there he is,
he's coming back from a you know from a journey overseas, a
diplomatic journey, and he lands in JFK and he's declaring all of
his objects and he's paying customs on it. Okay, he doesn't he
doesn't take it in through the diplomatic pouch. So תנו מכס למוכס.
Tnu mekhes lamokhes. אמרו לו, Amru lo,
they said to him, הלא כל המכס כולו שלך הוא, Halo kol
hamekhes kuloh shelkha hu, what do you mean? All of this money,
the tax money from the custom, is all going to you. Why
are you paying taxes on your own objects?
So אמר להם, Amar lahem, so he said to them, ממני ילמדו
כל עוברי דרכים Mimeni yilmedu kol ovrei derakhim
from me will learn all those who pass on the way, who
fly into LaGuardia, ולא יבריחו עצמן מן המכס Velo yavrikhi atzman min
hamekhes and they won't find ways to get away from paying customs.
I want to set the right example. Now by the way, I
should say parenthetically, this is fascinating because there are משניות בנדרים Mishnayot
bi-Nedarim that talk about making a false type of a נדר Neder
or it's not, you know, to a to a customs collector in
order to get out of paying the custom, and actually gives ways
in which technically that might be okay. And that leads to a
whole like discussion about you know whether you know about following governmental
laws and whether the tax collector, are they what they're doing is
just or not just? Is it an unjust government? Are they sort
of you know exploiting their position and taking more than they say
deserve to be taken and so on. So it's with that background
to appreciate that there's a משנה Mishna that actually talks about ways
of avoiding tax collectors. And here the גמרא's Gemara saying, no, God
is setting an example that you know people that go on the
ways should not try to find ways to avoid the tax collectors.
There's a very like practically relevant reality that it is seeking to.
You know, this was in a world of in Roman Palestine where
Rome
would be levying these taxes and are we supposed to give it
to this sort of oppressive government or not give it and so
on? So it's important I think to a, appreciate a little bit
of the historical and relevant context of that type of a statement.
How it's relevant for us is God wants to set the example.
Now, it's
not—it's not like the greatest parallel, maybe it's like a קל וחומר
*kal vachomer*. In this case, it's sort of like, you know, but
the argument, you know, it's like it's not like paying a tax
and doing your duty, it's more like if you stole, what's the
consequence of then, you know, fulfilling the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* with that?
But it seems that the parallel is the following: is that here
you are doing a מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*, so you're basically saying like,
you know, or you're bringing a קרבן korban *korban*, and you're saying,
"Look, all the animals belong to God, so why should God care
whether I'm bringing my קרבן korban *korban* or I'm taking Charlie's קרבן
korban. *korban* animal and doing it? It's all God's anyway, and I'm
just giving it back to God. I know why Charlie cares, but
why should God care?" Okay. And this says no, God does care.
When you go ahead and you even if you're bringing things to
God, you know, it can't come through a, you know,
through some type of a violation. God doesn't want to be condoning
that violation. And that's important because when the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* has
a very fascinating line when it deals with the idea of מצוה
הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah *mitzvah habah b'aveira*. It says—it says you
could frame it two ways: you could say אין עבירה aveirah מצוה
mitzvah, *ein aveira mitzvah*, a sin cannot become a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*.
You cannot go ahead and do a sin and then think it's
going to count for a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. God does not, you
know, want to condone this and allow it or whatever. But then
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says, "But you could say the opposite. You
could say אין מצוה mitzvah בעבירה *ein mitzvah b'aveira*. If I'm doing
a מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*, it can't get qualified as an עבירה aveirah.
*aveira*." And we sometimes say that. We sometimes say an idea like
say עשה דוחה לא תעשה *asei docheh lo ta'asei*. If I have
to put, you know, a string of a blue string in my
ציצית *tzitzit* and it has to be wool and I'm wearing a
linen garment, it's not a problem that it's שעטנז *shaatnez*, because an
עשה דוחה לא תעשה *asei docheh lo ta'asei*. The מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*
doesn't become an עבירה aveirah *aveira*, the מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* overrides concerns
of an עבירה *aveira*. So that's there's a logic to say, "Hey,
you're doing a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, it should override those types of
concerns." Okay, now, and therefore this is saying no, like again, exactly
when do we say מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah, *mitzvah habah
b'aveira*, fine, there's a very there are limited cases that define that,
but the general rule is just because you're doing a מצוה mitzvah
*mitzvah* doesn't condone an עבירה *aveira*, just because you're giving it back
to God doesn't mean that you can do something that is illegal,
immoral, a sin in that context. So here are the two the
two sources of מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah, *mitzvah habah b'aveira*.
Now, it's important to just say very briefly some questions about what
its parameters are. It's interesting to note that both of these sources
are about a קרבן *korban*, but the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* somehow assumes
you can immediately apply it to the question of the לולב lulav
*lulav*. So some ראשונים rishonim *Rishonim* say, "Fine, it's about a קרבן
*korban* but it's a general point about doing מצות *mitzvot* and it's
not—we don't say מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah *mitzvah habah b'aveira*."
The problem is that there are some גמרות *Gemarot* that don't seem
to know about the idea of מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah.
*mitzvah habah b'aveira*. Like a גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that speaks about a
stolen סוכה *sukkah* that raises the issue of ownership but it never
raises the issue of מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah, *mitzvah habah
b'aveira*. Or a גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that talks about eating מצה *matzah*
that's טבל *tevel*, that you're doing an עבירה *aveira* when you eat
the מצה *matzah* and it never talks about מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah
haba'ah ba'aveirah? *mitzvah habah b'aveira*. So what do you do about the
fact that some גמרות *Gemarot* are not aware of this concept?
So some wait
so
some say, "What about so what about this? לולב lulav *lulav*, קרבן
*korban*?" So some ראשונים *Rishonim* say, "You know what? You're right. מצוה
הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah. *mitzvah habah b'aveira* outside of קרבן *korban*
is only rabbinic, and those other גמרות *Gemarot* are talking at a
biblical level and the whole idea of מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah
ba'aveirah. *mitzvah habah b'aveira* maybe outside of the קרבן *korban* example is
only rabbinic." רמב"ן *Ramban* says something different which is quite important in
terms of thinking about the nature of לולב lulav *lulav*. When we
were talking about סוכה *sukkah*, we were talking about סוכה *sukkah* very
much, you know, in terms of the ענני הכבוד *ananei hakavod* and
how that whole sort of the strength of that metaphor. Well what
do you do with a לולב lulav *lulav*? With a לולב lulav
*lulav* you shake it, and when do you do it like during
הלל *Hallel*? And what's this whole idea of shaking and during הלל
*Hallel* and during דאווענינג *davening* and a very powerful sort of idea
behind לולב lulav *lulav*, it's a sort of a vehicle of תפילה
*tefillah*, it's a form of תפילה *tefillah*, you use it in the
acts of תפילה *tefillah*, particularly relating to water and praying for water.
So the רמב"ן *Ramban* says is מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah.
*mitzvah habah b'aveira* is only a problem in something like a קרבן
*korban*, meaning, and therefore biblically it applies to a לולב lulav, *lulav*
because you're coming to use it as a way of finding favor
with God, להרצות *lehirtzot*,
הירצה *heyartzeh* says the verse, right? If you bring a פיסח ועיוור
*pisei'ach v'ivveir*, you know, and how will it be desirous? So if
you're coming to sort of, you know, to appeal to God and
to connect to God directly, not just to do a מצוה mitzvah?
*mitzvah* like eating מצה *matzah*, sitting in a סוכה *sukkah*, again, now
סוכה *sukkah*'s on the other side of the equation, then maybe it's
not so problematic, but where it's deeply problematic is you're trying to
here basically say, "God, answer us, you know, God I'm trying to
connect with you," and you're involved in it with an עבירה *aveira*.
That actually is where it becomes particularly a problem. So there's an
interesting question of going from קרבן *korban* to other things and is
מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah *mitzvah habah b'aveira* a global principle
or not. One other comment about מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah
*mitzvah habah b'aveira*, I don't want to get into all the discussion
of the ראשונים *Rishonim* but I want to say— The other very
very fundamental conceptual idea about it is,
what does מצוה הבאה בעבירה, mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah does it invalidate the
act or does it invalidate the object? And here's what I mean
by that. The first statement of רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai is, it's similar to a lame animal. That seems to
focus on a stigma on the object, an invalidity on the object.
You can't use this object as a מצוה mitzvah object. So if
I were to have a מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveira. that
would not be about the object being problematic, I would be doing
an עבירה when I'm doing a מצוה, mitzvah but it's not about
the object of the מצוה, mitzvah. then that might be okay and,
I mean not okay to do it, but that might not invalidate
the מצוה. mitzvah So for example, the question is, let's say you
stole a שופר, shofar, are you יוצא yotzei or not, and you
blow it? So the רמב"ם Rambam quoting a ירושלמי Yerushalmi says you're
יוצא, yotzei, why? Because he says you're not doing the מצוה mitzvah
technically with the שופר, shofar, you're doing the מצוה with the sound,
and the sound isn't stolen, only the שופר shofar is stolen. Sounds
like a very creative argument. But the point is, is that the
idea is that it invalidates the object, and therefore sometimes if it's
not focused on what we define as the exact object of the
מצוה, you would still be יוצא. yotzei. That's one way of thinking
it. It stigmatizes the object if it was stolen.
The first two words of the משנה, Mishnah, it doesn't say he's
not יוצא yotzei his, he says the לולב lulav is פסול. pasul.
Exactly, excellent.
And exactly, the לשון lashon of the משנה Mishnah says לולב הגזול
והיבש פסול, lulav hagazul vehayavesh pasul, the לולב lulav. is invalid.
And the רמב"ם Rambam when he talks about מצוה הבאה בעבירה, mitzvah
haba'ah b'aveirah. he lists גזול gazul with all these things, and he
says if it's invalid for any one of these blemishes, basically is
the way the רמב"ם Rambam says. You know, he sort of categorizes
it with issues of like blemishes on the on the object. So
that's one way, probably, you know, a very straightforward way and very
consistent. The other way that talks more about God setting an example
does not seem to focus on the object, seems to focus on
the action. What are you doing? You're stealing, I can't condone that
and so on. And that would say, no, no, the problem is
when the action of the מצוה is intertwined with the עבירה. But
the question still becomes, how do you define intertwined? Right? Because there
are cases with let's say I'm shaking a לולב lulav here and
eating a ham sandwich here. That's not a מצוה הבאה בעבירה, mitzvah
haba'ah b'aveirah, right? What does it mean to be connected to and
intertwined with? Stealing is a great example. I wouldn't have the לולב
lulav if I hadn't stolen. So that really makes it intertwined with
the sin. It's enabled me to be doing the sin. There are
other cases where it's not so intertwined and that might be considered
okay. You're doing a sin and doing a מצוה, but it's not
בה, bah, it's not coming through it. So again, two separate ways
of way the question of scope. Does it apply biblically by all
מצוות mitzvot or just by קרבן or just by קרבן and לולב
lulav. and things like that? And number two, what's its exact nature?
Is it about invalidating the object? So we have to ask the
question about which object is the מצוה object and whether this object
has a label or doesn't have a label. And let me give
you, by the way, another interesting example of that. Let's say I
carried my לולב lulav on שבת Shabbat and I put it and
then I came to שול, shul, I shook it. Well, I did
an עבירה and in a way bringing it was part of me
at least shaking it in שול, shul, in some way it enabled
or whatever. But if you carry an object, does it become labeled?
Does the object now get stigmatized? Right? A stolen object is labeled
with its identity as, you know, as its problematic nature becomes part
of its identity. The fact that I carried a לולב, lulav it's
like that's my problem, that's not the לולב lulav. problem. It doesn't
change the identity of the לולב. Lulav. So that's one question, is
we have to identify the object and we have to ask is
the thing that was done, does it stigmatize the object or not?
Whereas the other approach says it's not about the object, it's about
the act you did is enabling. You're sinning, you're doing a מצוה
through sinning, not through a sinned object, but through sinning. And then
the question we have to ask is what does through mean? How
much do they have to be related to somehow invalidate the performance
of the מצוה? Okay, so that's a very quick שיעור shiur on
מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah. and it very nicely links to
the two sources in the גמרא. Gemara Let's continue now in the
גמרא. Gemara It says like this, איתמר, itmar, was taught. איתמר נמי
אמר רבי אמי, itmar nami amar Rabbi Ami, יבש פסול מפני שאין
הדר. yavesh pasul mipnei she'ein hadar. So he says that a dried
up לולב Lulav is invalid because it is not הדר, hadar, that
we know. וגזול פסול משום דהוי ליה מצוה הבאה בעבירה. vegazul pasul
mishum dehavei leih mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah. And stolen's invalid because of מצוה
הבאה בעבירה. mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah So you see that there is this
concept and presumably that concept explains why it's invalid for all seven
days. ופליגא דרבי יצחק, upliga deRabbi Yitzchak, and this argues on רבי
יצחק. Rabbi Yitzchak. דאמר רבי יצחק בר נחמני אמר שמואל, de'amar Rabbi
Yitzchak bar Nachmani amar Shmuel, because now we have a statement in
the name of שמואל. Shmuel. לא שנו אלא ביום טוב ראשון. lo
shanu ela beyom tov rishon. The invalidity of stolen is only on
the first day of יום טוב. Yom Tov. אבל ביום טוב שני,
aval beyom tov sheini, on the other days of יום טוב, Yom
Tov, מתוך שיוצא בשאול, mitoch sheyotzei beshaul, because you could use a
borrowed object, because there is no requirement of ownership, יוצא נמי בגזול,
yotzei nami begazul, stolen is not a problem. The only issue with
stolen is that you don't own it. There is no concept of
מצוה הבאה בעבירה, mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah, and therefore... Stolen is כשר kosher
on the other days of חול המועד Chol HaMoed just the same
way a borrowed is. So מתיב רב נחמן בר יצחק, masive Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak asks
on that: לולב הגזול והיבש פסול. lulav hagazul vehayavesh pasul. So it
says stolen and dried up is invalid. Now before we tried to
underscore the same way dried up is all seven days, stolen is
all seven days. So maybe you could say, okay no, not necessarily.
But I've got, but still I'm going to try to prove my
case from the language of the משנה. Mishna. Because it says stolen
is invalid. So the implication is stolen is invalid, השאול כשר, hashaul
kasher, borrowed is permissible. So אימת, eimas, when would that be that
borrowed is permissible? אילימא ביום טוב ראשון, ileima beYom Tov rishon, if
it's on the first day יום טוב, Yom Tov, הא כתיב 'לכם'
משלכם, ha ksiv 'lachem' mishalechem, we know you can't use a borrowed
לולב Lulav and אתרוג esrog on the first day. ולאו דידיה הוא,
velav dideih hu, it's not yours. אלא לאו ביום טוב שני, ela
lav beYom Tov sheni, it must be we're talking on the second
day of יום טוב, Yom Tov, meaning on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed.
That would be the only case when שאול shaul would be okay.
That's why the משנה Mishna doesn't mention שאול shaul and it still
mentions גזול. gazul. וקתני גזול פסול. vekatani gazul pasul.
So you see that גזול gazul is invalid even when you can
use a borrowed לולב. Lulav. That seems a very strong argument. So
אמר רבא, amar Rava, the גרסא girsa is changed to: לעולם ביום
טוב ראשון. le'olam beYom Tov rishon. No, we're going to still say
our משנה Mishna's limited to the first day יום טוב. Yom Tov.
ולא מבעיא קאמר, velo mibaiya ka'amar, it goes without saying. Meaning why
doesn't it say therefore שאול shaul is invalid? Yeah, that's more obvious
than גזול. gazul. Really? Borrowed is a more obvious invalidity than stolen?
Yeah. לא מבעיא שאול, lo mibaiya shaul, it goes without saying that
borrowed is invalid, דלאו דידיה הוא, delav dideih hu, because you have
no ownership over it. אבל גזול, aval gazul, when you steal
it, אימא סתם גזילה יאוש בעלים הוא, eima stam gezeilah yeiush be'alim
hu, maybe I'll say like we were suggesting before, that with stealing
comes, especially you have to understand that גזול gazul means sort of
like robbery, meaning that it's in, you steal it directly from the
owner, it's not burglary. So the owner knows it's stolen. So immediately
with robbery comes a יאוש, yeiush, the owner giving up, and therefore
maybe by גזול gazul you really do own it. And that's why
I might think it's כשר. kosher. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan
that it's invalid, that it's not כשר. kosher. Why not? Maybe because
of מצוה הבאה בעבירה? mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah, Maybe only in the first
day. But more likely he's saying because you don't own it after
יאוש. yeiush. Okay, so here's an approach that rejects מצוה הבאה בעבירה.
mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah, Certainly rejects it on the other days. On the
other days you can use borrowed, no problem. You could use stolen,
no problem. The only issue is the first day. The משנה Mishna's
only talking about the first day. It could have said that borrowed
was invalid as well, but it says גזול gazul to tell you
even though you stolen it and now you might think you own
it, nevertheless you don't own it, or nevertheless maybe there's still some
מצוה הבאה בעבירה. mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah, But whatever it is, it's only
limited to the first day when borrowed is invalid as well, it's
not an issue on the rest of the days. So here seems
to be a very deep debate whether we believe in this principle
of מצוה הבאה בעבירה. mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah, Again, you could try to
limit the debate and say, no no, we all believe in the
principle on the first day, we're debating whether you say the principle
on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, okay. But it sounds like there's a
deeper debate of whether you actually believe in the principle of מצוה
הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah? and whether גזול gazul is a problem
because of that or is גזול gazul a problem because you just
don't own it. And I should by the way add, I hope
I'm not overloading all of you with all this information, but if
we say that גזול gazul only means on the first day, then
it could also be that the word יבש yavesh also means only
on the first day. And this gets back to the issue I
told you where חכמי ספרד Chachmei Sefarad basically want to limit all
the invalidities to the first day. And now that's what's being done
right
right here, is that he's saying the משנה Mishna's talking about גזול
gazul and גזול gazul is only, and it's only talking, the משנה,
גזול gazul is only talking about the first day. So if the
משנה Mishna's only talking about the first day, that might be true
about all of the משנה. Mishna. Okay, and that becomes an important
הלכה halacha question. There's a ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says that. ירושלמי says
all of the פסולים psulim were only said ביום הראשון, beYom HaRishon,
on the first day. And it's worth noting that that very much
fits into the statement right now about שמואל Shmuel that limits the
case of גזול gazul to the first day.
ולא מבעיא קאמר velo mibaiya ka'amar is rejected, וקא משמע לן, veka
mashma lan, right? Is that how, right?
קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that גזול gazul is invalid, right?
It's invalid. Invalid.
You can't make the חילוק chiluk between the שאול shaul
and the גזול, gazul, right. So we have two important issues here.
One is is there a principle of מצוה הבאה בעבירה at all?
Seems to be being debated. And we had a whole discussion what
מצוה הבאה בעבירה meant. And number two is whether גזול gazul or
relatedly whether גזול gazul is invalid the first day or the other
days. And that though could mean whether the whole משנה Mishna is
talking about the first day or the other days, whether the other
invalidities apply throughout the חג chag or just on the first day,
an issue I mentioned before. Okay, so now we're going to turn
to a very interesting application of these concerns. אמר להו רבא, amar
lehu Rava, רב הונא Rav Huna להנהו אבנקלי. lahanei avankli. So two
lines from the bottom. רב הונא Rav Huna said to the
merchants
the following...
So let's take a look. This way רש״י Rashi interprets the word
אבנטרי. avantri.
כי זבניתו אסא מעכו״ם Ki zavnitu asa me-akum when you are going
to buy הדס, hadas, הדסים hadasim from the non-Jews, לא תגזו אתון
אלא לגזוזה אינהו. lo tagzu atun ela ligzoza inehu. Don't you be
the ones to cut the הדסים hadasim off the tree, let them
be the ones to cut the הדסים hadasim off the tree, ויהב
לך ve-yahv lach and then give it to you. So you're going
around, you're buying הדסים hadasim for the Jewish community, and the people
that own the הדסים hadasim are these non-Jews that have all of
these fields with הדס hadas trees in them. So have them be
the ones to cut it off the tree, not you. Why? מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason? סתם עובדי כוכבים גזלני ארעתא נינהו.
Stam ovdei kochavim gazlanei arata ninhu. So that's obviously a very troublesome
statement, but was probably reflecting a reality at that time and place,
that the non-Jews are assumed to be on land that is not
technically theirs, okay? They own it, doesn't necessarily mean they stick people
up at gunpoint, but maybe it means that they take possession of
it, maybe the government took possession of it, and the הלכה halacha
doesn't recognize the base on which the government seized possession of it,
you know, to be legitimate, and therefore it's considered גזל. gezel. By
the way, the ערוך Aruch says that the word אבנטרי avantri doesn't
just mean merchants, it means sort of like officers of the king.
So it is connected to some degree to governmental issues. Anyway, so
we have to assume in this context that the land that they're
on is not theirs. So it's גזל. gezel. All right, so now
we're going to have a problem. You're going to buy a הדס
hadas from them and therefore you're going to be יוצא yotzei the
מצוה of לולב with a stolen הדס. hadas.
Where did רב הונא Rav Huna live?
In בבל. Bavel.
Okay, so so it's you're going to be doing the מצוה with
a stolen הדס. hadas. So here's how you're going to get out
of it, because part of the issue also has to do with
the fact of that we start with the idea of לענן. le'anan.
So let's keep on reading. קרקע אינה נגזלת. Karka eina nigzelet. Land
cannot be stolen. Okay, now that's of course you gotta love sort
of the thing. You know, we assume all the land is stolen
and land can't be stolen. So what does it mean land can't
be stolen? It means הלכה halachically its status doesn't change, the status
of the land. You still sin if you seize somebody else's property,
but of course you can't put somebody's land in your back pocket
and take it away. It's always there. So in a way, you
know, you're forcing the owner off, but you're not like taking it
physically away from the owner. And therefore הלכה, halachically, the land never
gets an identity as being stolen. You stole, but the land, that
identity never applies to the land. So for example, when the גמרא
Gemara thinks that you could let's say be קונה koneh something with
יאוש, yeiush, right? If I stole a לולב and there's יאוש, yeiush,
I take possession, that would not apply to land. I basically seize
your land, you gave up hope of ever getting it back, it
doesn't become my land. It's still always there and it's always your
land. Okay, so now these lands are being are seized by people
that are not their owners, and they have הדס hadas trees, but
the הדס hadas trees are connected to the ground. So there's yet
no status change in the land and in the הדס hadas trees.
Okay, now let's see what happens once those הדסים hadasim are cut
down and then they become chattel and not
land. Okay, הלכך hilkach לגזוזה אינהו, ligzoza inehu, let them cut it
down, כי היכי דהוי יאוש בעלים בידייהו. ki heichi de-havei yeiush be-alim
be-yadaihu. Now what's going to happen? They're going to cut it down,
and then the fact that the owners have, look, this land has
been stolen for the last decade. The owners have long given up
hope of ever getting it back. The only point is as I
said, their giving up hope, their יאוש, yeiush, has not changed the
status of the land because it's always there. So when will it
be meaningful? When you cut down the הדסים. hadasim. Now these הדסים
hadasim are stolen as well, right? They're just no longer land. Now
they're stolen הדסים hadasim that isn't land. Now the יאוש yeiush of
the owners from 10 years ago kicks in. Now this thing which
can be defined as stolen is both stolen and stolen with the
owners giving up hope. And that means that I can take possession
of it, right? After יאוש yeiush and its chattel and it's stolen,
now it can be possessed. So therefore, what will happen? If the
non-Jews are the ones that cut it down, then who is the
first one who winds up owning these
הדסים? hadasim? The non-Jews. Now you buy it from the non-Jews, when
you're buying it, it's not considered a מצוה הבאה בעבירה. If you
cut it down and then you took possession of it as, you
know, in the initial act of being like taking it when it
was stolen and then becoming yours, but it went from being stolen
to being yours, that's what the גמרא Gemara. said before. Even after
יאוש, yeiush, even after you take possession of it, right, it remains
invalid, right? That was the whole point about the קרבן. Even if
you own it, you stole it, even now that you own it,
it remains invalid. But here, you're not you won't have, you know,
if you're going to let somebody else
be... By the time you come around, you're buying something that is
owned by them. So what do I care about its past history?
It's right now owned by the person on the land, and therefore
I can buy it and I don't have to relate to this
object as a stolen object. I don't have to care about its
past history. The past history is completely unrelated to me, because when
I encountered it, it was already owned by the owners of the
land. One minute, let's just finish reading
that. ושנוי סו וייאוש בעלים בידייהו דידהו, V'shinoi so v'ye'ush be'alim b'yadaihu
didehu, the ייאוש בעלים ye'ush be'alim will take effect when they're holding
onto it, ושינוי רשות בידייכו, v'shinoi reshus b'yadaichu, and when it comes
into your hands, then it'll change possession and then you'll be safe,
you'll be protected. So the גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, I
don't understand what's the problem for having these merchants cut it down?
סוף סוף כי גזו אבנתרי, Sof sof ki gazzu avanteri, when the
merchants cut it, let the merchants be the one to cut it
down. They have a ייאוש בעלים בידייהו, ye'ush be'alim b'yadaihu, so fine,
when will the ייאוש ye'ush kick in? It'll kick in in the
hands of the merchant. But nevertheless, the merchants are selling it to
somebody else. ושינוי רשות בידן, V'shinoi reshus b'yadan, we'll buy it from
the merchants and we're safe, cause the ייאוש ye'ush already took effect
in the hands of the merchants. So let the merchants cut it.
What do I care? I'm buying it from the merchants, so I'll
get it, it'll still be safe. So the גמרא Gemara says look,
צריכא באושענא דאבנתרי גופייהו. Tzricha b'oshana d'avanteri gufaihu. No, cause the merchants
themselves want to use the הדסים hadasim for their own לולב. So
for the merchants, you're right, if the merchant cut it down and
then sold it to you, by the time it got into your
hands, its past history like its record would have been expunged because
of for you. But not for the merchant, the merchant still encountered
it as a stolen object. So if the merchants want to use
it for themselves, they have to let the non-Jews cut it down,
get somebody else to do that dirty work, and then they can
encounter it after its slate has already been cleaned, after that is
just ancient history. Yes, Charlie.
This principle should apply everywhere in the world, not just ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael in terms of stolen land.
Yeah, so
I cannot have a willow tree or a myrtle bush in my
yard because my land was clearly stolen from the Indians.
No, so that gets to issues about דינא דמלכותא דינא Dina d'malchuta
dina and the idea that the government that also there's a particular
concept of כיבוש מלחמה kivush milchama that lands conquered in war, although
you could say was it really a war, was it a go
back on a treaty and this and that? Anyway, but there are
things that sort of recognize governmental actions history. Sometimes the גמרא Gemara,
questions whether the governmental actions are legitimate and therefore is it considered
גזול gazul or not. But once you introduce the principle of דינא
דמלכותא דינא, Dina d'malchuta dina, that tends to sort of recognize generally
the legitimacy of governmental actions for הלכה halacha purposes as well. Okay,
so that's how this גמרא. Gemara So what's fascinating about this גמרא
Gemara besides the idea of קרקע karka is that it recognizes that
it's not always מצוה הבאה בעבירה. Its label and identity does not
have to be permanent. Right, the גמרא Gemara before first set out
to say you stole, then even after you own it it remains
invalid. But for somebody else, that might be ancient history. Now, I
actually simplified it a little bit, because what I actually sort of
implied the scenario
was, here's the merchant, and here's the הדס hadas tree, anyway, he
has the הדס. hadas. So this is ייאוש ye'ush kicks in here.
And I said basically, ייאוש ye'ush kicked in when he when well
whatever whoever whoever bought it, the merchant or whoever cut it down,
ייאוש ye'ush kicked in and then going on the previous גמרא, Gemara
now he owns it. Now it's his. And here you come along,
we'll make you with the כיפה, kippah, here you come along and
you're buying something from him that he already owns. And therefore you're
totally clean. For you it's not גזול, gazul, he already owns it.
And that's what the גמרא Gemara says, yeah. But the גמרא Gemara
says, notice the language of the גמרא Gemara is ייאוש ye'ush plus
שינוי רשות. shinoi reshus. And that might suggest because a normal remember
I told you before there's a question whether ייאוש ye'ush itself makes
you own it. The normal assumption is ייאוש ye'ush itself doesn't make
you own it. If I'm the גזלן gazlan and I steal it,
even after ייאוש ye'ush I never own it. But then if I
hand it off to you, then you who are getting it after
ייאוש, ye'ush, you do own it. That's ייאוש ye'ush plus שינוי רשות.
shinoi reshus. In that scenario, even after ייאוש ye'ush he doesn't own
it. If there's ייאוש, ye'ush, it's still not his. It's still גזול.
gazul. There's ייאוש ye'ush and it's גזול. gazul. And then he transfers
it to him, then you have ייאוש ye'ush plus שינוי רשות, shinoi
reshus, and now after that act of transfer, here's where this guy
now owns it. Now why am I making that point? Because that's
a bigger חידוש chiddush in terms of the מצוה הבאה בעבירה, that
even though he encountered it, it was still גזול. gazul. You see
how he encountered it, it was still גזול, gazul, since at that
very act of taking it, it became his in that moment, that
makes it okay to use. That is a bigger חידוש chiddush than
saying after he owns it, you can buy it from him. Here
you can buy it while... While it's stolen, and in that act
of taking it though, it fully becomes yours. Okay, so that is
definitely a חידוש chiddush here and I want to point out by
the way that you will notice that this גמרא Gemara is not
doesn't mention the words מצוה הבאה בעבירה. And there are some ראשונים
that have understood that we're talking, you know, we already introduced the
possibility that maybe מצוה הבאה בעבירה we don't don't believe in the
concept. So maybe this whole גמרא Gemara is not about מצוה הבאה
בעבירה, maybe it's just about the need to own it, the need
for ownership, exact simple. Forget מצוה הבאה בעבירה, it's all about ownership.
So if you had a problem of מצוה הבאה בעבירה, you would
want him to own it fully and ייאוש yeiush to work before
you encountered it. But if you don't have a problem of מצוה
הבאה בעבירה, you can buy it even while it's still stolen. Okay,
it's stolen and I bought it, fine. But if it's not מצוה
הבאה בעבירה, I only care about one question: Do I own it?
And then, yes, even though when you bought it, it was stolen,
since you're going to own it in the end, you can use
it for the מצוה. So there's that big question: Is the גמרא
Gemara here trying to address the issue of ownership or is it
trying to, and that's sufficient, once you own it we're happy, or
is it also trying to address the issue of מצוה הבאה בעבירה?
So I can rest assured that the guy selling watches on 47th
street, those watches are stolen and I can buy one of those
watches and I don't have to worry.
I'm not going to answer that, we'll talk about it when we
get to בבא קמא. Bava Kamma.
Is it an applicable question? Yes, yes, as a concept.
Yes, yes,
that is correct.
Yes, the same question like stolen art or something. Right.
So okay, this gets to the question about the legality of engaging
in it and providing a market for the גנב ganav and the
גזלן gazlan and becoming sort of caught up in that sin, meaning
there's one question of do you own it after the
fact? And maybe the answer is yes, there was ייאוש yeiush and
שינוי רשות shinui reshus and whatever. The other question is are you
allowed to do it? And there is explicit discussions in בבא קמא
Bava Kamma about whether you are allowed to buy things that you
should that you can reasonably assume are stolen. And, you know, the
basic answer is no, and there's a reasonable assumption that they're stolen,
you cannot be buying it. So the question therefore can be so
like how can therefore you be buying these הדסים, hadassim, you know,
from this case of the קרקע karka and so on? But again,
it might be talking about a very different type of a reality.
It's one thing that your buying of it provides a market for
the goods and then you become complicit in the sin. It's another
thing here, the people are not stealing the land whatever the story
about that is, they're not stealing the land in order so that
they can make a fortune selling הדסים hadassim on סוכות. Succos. You
know, so it's really... so but there are issues definitely with buying
stolen goods and providing a market. That's being bracketed here. Okay, but
it is important to raise the issue. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: So in order for the merchants to take
possession, to take possession
of it, they need the owners to cut it down. And then
for themselves, again for their own לולב ואתרוג, Lulav and Esrog, they
can use it because then it'll they'll take possession with ייאוש yeiush
plus the שינוי רשות shinui reshus plus the switching of the hands.
So the גמרא Gemara says okay וליקנינהו בשינוי מעשה. ve'likninhu b'shinui ma'aseh.
Why do you have to worry about, you know, ייאוש ושינוי רשות
yeiush v'shinui reshus and transferring ownership? Let them cut it down and
they'll own it. Why will they own it? I mean ייאוש yeiush
itself doesn't do it, it has to change hands. No, they'll own
it because they made a physical change in the object. Now what
is the physical change they made in the object? They cut it
down. Interestingly, the גמרא Gemara does not seem to care be focusing
on that. The גמרא Gemara. assumes the physical change in the object
is they're going to take the הדס hadas and bind it into
the לולב. And that's the change. So the גמרא Gemara says no
כסבר לולב אין צריך אגד. kasavar Lulav ein tzarich eged. Look, you
know, לולב doesn't have to be bound up and therefore even if
you did bind it up, it doesn't create a new identity to
the object. It's tied with other things, but it's not a הלכתית
halachically new identity and it's meaningless. ואי תמצי לומר לולב צריך אגד
v'im timtzi lomar Lulav tzarich eged and even if it did require
an אגד eged and now it has a new identity, it's like
you changed it and made it part of a לולב bunch, nevertheless
שינוי החוזר לברייתו הוא. shinui hachozer livriyaso hu. It's going to be
a change that is going to revert back to form. After סוכות
Succos it's going to lose that special identity and it'll just become
a simple הדס. hadas. ושינוי החוזר לברייתו לא שמיה שינוי. v'shinui hachozer
livriyaso lo shemeih shinui. And something that reverts back to form is
not considered a real change. So of course this גמרא Gemara is
wild because it assumes that cutting it down is not a significant
change. You know, okay, it's a growing הדס hadas or not a
growing הדס. hadas. I mean but you know maybe it's not so
crazy. Like let's say we were talking not about a הדס hadas
which is a branch and it does seem like more of a
change. Let's say we were talking about an apple. Okay, and I
told you this principle that when you make a שינוי shinui in
an object, the idea here is how does a גזלן gazlan take
possession, ownership—not that it's legal—but take ownership of the object he stole.
One way is the concept of ייאוש. yeiush. ייאוש ושינוי רשות. yeiush
v'shinui reshus. That's about creating a distancing the object from the owner
because he's given up hope, it's out of his control, now maybe
even a third party has taken possession of it after the ייאוש.
yeiush. That creates that distancing and that's how it works. But another
way a גזלן gazlan takes possession is when he makes a... changes
the object, then it becomes not like not the original thing that
was stolen and therefore that also makes it something that is no
longer considered to be the owner's. He has to pay back the
owner, don't get me wrong, and none of this is permissible, but
with that שינוי, shinoy, it somehow changes the identity of the object,
not the distancing, but the identity. So let's say, so we're all
saying, well, so I don't understand, isn't that physical change? Cutting it
is a big physical change. But let's say we're talking about an
apple, okay? And let's say I said you plucked an apple off
of a tree. You stole somebody's land that had an apple tree
and you plucked an apple. Should that be considered to be that
you've changed it now and it's a שינוי מעשה shinoy ma'aseh and
you and you don't have to return the object? So we say,
no, you know, okay, it was growing and now you plucked it,
but it's still the same apple, it's just no longer attached. Now,
we do feel a little bit differently about a branch, which is
like central to which is like part of the tree and something
growing off of the tree that will fall off on its own.
But that seems to be the גמרא's Gemara. understanding. Cutting down the
הדסים Hadasim doesn't really change the הדס. Hadas. But maybe what changes
it is they became part of the לולב. And then, nah, that's
not a change in any way, that's going to revert back to
before. So you can't own it that way. You still need this
idea of יאוש ושינוי רשות. ye'ush ve'shinoy reshus. So you need them
to cut it and then you buy it, so by the time
you buy it, now it has transferred ownership and now you're okay.
I steal your car and I stole it, then I chop it
into different pieces. I own the pieces?
Yes, exactly. You bring it to a chop shop, you own the
pieces.
The same right to the pieces? A fender is now mine? Exactly.
I got to pay for your car, but the fender's mine.
Exactly. Exactly. Okay, so let's just see one more line of the
גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא says: ולקנייה
בשינוי השם. ve'likniyeh be'shinoy ha'shem. Okay, but what about a change in
name? Now, what change in name occurs to this? So, מעיקרא הוי
ליה אסא והשתא הושענא. me'ikara havei lei asa ve'hashta hoshana. Before, it
was a myrtle. Before סוכות Succos came along, it was a myrtle
branch. Comes along סוכות, Succos, and it's no longer a myrtle branch.
It's a הדס. Hadas. Okay? So the effect that it's being used
for a מצוה gives it a new identity. So in the גמרא's
language, the הדסא hadasa was הדס, hadas, that was just the you
know but the normal botanical name for this thing. But when it's
a מצוה object, its name is now הושענא. Hoshana. So doesn't that
now change its identity and mean you should own it even without
changing hands? So just see the one answer of the גמרא. The
גמרא's answer is: מעיקרא נמי לאסא הושענא קרי ליה. me'ikara nami le'asa
hoshana kari lei. You know what? They were calling it a הדס,
Hadas, they were calling it a הושענא Hoshana even before סוכות, Succos,
right? Especially right once it gets to be like תשרי, Tishrei, you're
looking around and you're seeing what what a month ago you would
have called a willow, now you're calling an ערבה. arava. And what
a month ago you would have called a myrtle, now you're calling
a הדס. Hadas. So therefore, it is actually the name existed even
before it was cut down and therefore the only way to own
it is have the יאוש ye'ush kick in when they cut it
down and then you buy it and then it's יאוש ושינוי רשות
ye'ush ve'shinoy reshus and now you own it and that will allow
you to use it. Okay.